Guide to the Walton Family Papers, 1730-1980 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Walton Family papers 1730-1980 and undated
Walton family
3.1 linear feet Extent: 1633 Items.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
walton
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of the Walton family (1730-1975) were donated to the Special Collections Department from 1984-1987 by Mrs. Loring B. Walton, Loring B. Walton, and Eleanore Walton Bequaert.
Biographical Note
George E. Walton
1839, Dec. 25 Born in Cincinnati, Ohio to Charles and Sarah Underwood Horsey Blake Walton
1864 Graduated from Bellevue Medical College (N.Y.). Served as Assistant Surgeon in the Union Army
1865 Toured Europe to study methods of surgery and medicine
1866 Began medical practice in Cincinnati, Ohio
ca. 1870 Married Marion Young of Pittsburg, Pa. Had two sons and two daughters
1880 Assumed Chair of Medicine and Surgery at Cincinnati Academy of Medicine
1880-1881 President of Cincinnati Academy of Medicine
1883 Published
The Mineral Springs of the United States and Canada with Analyses and Notes on the Prominent Spas of Europe, and a List of Sea-Side Resorts (D. Appleton)
1890 Moved to DeLand, Fla. area
1892, Fall Married Eleanore C. Baker in St. Augustine, Fla. Son was Loring Baker Walton
1917, June 25 Died in Terre Haute, Ind.
Eleanore C. Walton
1865, Mar. 18 Born Eleanore “Nellie” Coolidge Baker in Hingham, Mass. to Susan L. and James Loring Baker
1880s Attended Hingham Academy (Hingham, Mass.). Studied in Chicago
1891 Moved to Florida because of illness where she was treated by George E. Walton
1892, Fall Married George E. Walton in St. Augustine, Fla. Son was Loring Baker Walton
ca. 1898 Moved to Kansas City, Mo. and became active on the Board of the Women's and Children's Hospital, and in the Missouri Society for Crippled Children, the Women's Chamber of Commerce, the YWCA, and the 2nd District Federation of Women's Clubs for Missouri
1933, May Appointed Assistant to Film Censor for Kansas City
1938, Dec. Appointed Film Censor for Kansas City
1948 Retired and moved to Durham, N.C.
1958, July 12 Died in Durham, N.C.
Loring Baker Walton
1893, Nov. 17 Born in Deland, Fla. to Eleanore C. and George E. Walton
1898 Moved to Kansas City, Mo. with his mother
1916 A.B. degree from Princeton University. Entered Harvard University as a graduate student
1918-1920 Served in the U.S. Army in France, Germany, and Utah
1920, Nov. Employed by Guaranty Trust Company in New York City
1923(?) Returned to Europe for study and travel
1924 License-es-Lettres from the Sorbonne in Paris in classical languages
1924-1929 Instructor of Romance Languages at Princeton University
1925, Dec. Married Susanne Joseph Lindlar. Children were Loring B. Walton, Jr. and Eleanore
1929-1963 Professor of Romance Languages at Duke University
1943 Ph.D. degree from the University of Chicago
1975, Feb. 9 Died in Durham, N.C.
Published:
Anatole France and the Greek World (Duke University Press: 1950),
A Manuscript of Thais (PMLA: 1956),
and
Anatole France and the First World War: the Correspondence with Carlos Blacker (PMLA: 1962).
Collection Overview
The Walton Family Papers, 1730 to 1975 (bulk 1880-1975), include journals and diaries; correspondence; writings; pictorial material such as postcards, photographs, albums and negatives; clippings; mimeographed material; printed material; and genealogical material. While the majority of the collection pertains to Loring Baker Walton, there also is a family focus, primarily in the correspondence throughout the papers. In particular it relates to Loring Walton, his mother Eleanore C. Walton, her father James Baker, and Eleanore Walton's husband George E. Walton. The collection relates only peripherally to their careers.
The lives of George and Eleanore Walton are documented in the George and Eleanore Walton Series. Most of the earliest items pertain to Mrs. Walton's family, the Bakers, who had settled in Hingham, Massachusetts at least by the eighteenth-century. Letters to Mrs. Walton comprise a major segment of this series, including those to her from her father, James Baker, 1880-1882. Included are courtship letters from George Walton, a physician who attended Eleanore Walton while she was convalescing near Deland, Florida. Most were written, 1891-1892, after she returned to her home in Chicago. Letters from George Walton after the marriage suggest financial hardship and indicate that the couple was frequently separated from the beginning of their marriage and during the early childhood of their son Loring. After 1895, there is a gap in the correspondence. Included is George Walton's 1896 diary of a trip via wagon from Indiana to Florida. Later material and correspondence in the series pertains to Eleanore Walton's work as a clubwoman and motion picture censor in Kansas City, Missouri from the 1920s to 1948, when she retired and moved to Durham, N.C. to live with her son Loring Walton.
The first series is a preview to the second, much larger Loring B. Walton Series. Four volumes of journal entries describe Walton's daily life and thought as a student, first in Kansas City, Mo., and later at Princeton University, which he entered in 1912. The journals record campus reaction to Woodrow Wilson's election to the presidency. Walton was a graduate student at Harvard when he was discharged from ROTC, called to active duty in the U.S. Army, and assigned to the American Expeditionary Force in France and Germany in 1918-1919. During the war and its aftermath, Walton assembled postcards and some photographs which complement his journal entries and correspondence. Most of his letters in this series are addressed to his mother, Eleanore C. Walton, with a few to his grandmother and aunt in Kansas City, Mo. Of interest are his characterizations of civilians during the war and occupation as well as his view of political conditions. For over 30 years Walton corresponded with A. Goderic A. Hodges, a British Army officer who lost a leg while in balloon service.
To a limited extent there is information in the Loring B. Walton Series about Walton's literary and scholarly interests. A small quantity of correspondence is from authors such as Wilmon Brewer, Count Sforza, and Maurice Holleaux. Included is a letter written by Anatole France, which was given to Walton, and a handwritten, signed poem by Edmund Wilson. There are several draft versions of Walton's addresses or articles, mostly undated. While there are no papers or correspondence relating to Walton's study at the Sorbonne, one address refers to his living in the home of a French family and his observations of French culture and educational methods. This series also thinly documents his involvement with Duke University through the Interdenominational Church and the Erasmus Club, and his sabbatical in Europe while a member of the Department of Romance Languages.
Addition (03-053) (175 items, .2 lin. ft.; dated 1917-1968) comprises materials of Loring Baker Walton, and consists primarily of scholarly correspondence and materials concerning his work on Anatole France and other projects (1932-1968). Also includes his class notes from Harvard (1917-1918), and from his training and service with the American Expeditionary Forces during World War I. This addition is unprocessed.
Addition (08-184) (375 items, .4 lin. ft.; dated 1891-1980 and undated) contains primarily material related to Loring Baker Walton’s background and service with the AEF in WWI. Includes information regarding Walter family property settlements for land they owned in Germany that was damaged during WWII. There are also letters (1891-1951) for George E. and Eleanore C. Walter. This addition is unprocessed.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Sforza, Carlo, Conte, 1872-1952.; France, Anatole, 1844-1924.; Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972.; Baker family.; Baker family.; Great Britain. Army -- Officers -- Correspondence.; Great Britain. Army -- Officers -- Correspondence.; United States. Army -- Officers -- Correspondence.; United States. Army -- Officers -- Correspondence.; Courtship.; Authors, European.; College students.; Walton, George E.,; Walton, Elanor C.,; Walton, Loring Baker; Women -- Societies and clubs.; World War, 1914-1918 -- France.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Germany.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Germany.; Hingham (Mass.)--History
Contents of Collection
- George and Eleanore Walton Series
  George and Eleanore Walton, 1730-1958 and undated (bulk 1880-1949). Diary, letters, clippings, photographs, and printed material, but consists chiefly of letters to Eleanore. Two categories: correspondence and miscellaneous.
  - Correspondence:
    - Early family, 1830-1835 (Box 1)
    - James L. Baker to Eleanore, 1880-1886, undated
    - George to Eleanore, 1891-1895 and undated, (3 folders)
    - Other correspondents to Eleanore, 1887-1949
  - Miscellaneous:
    - Clippings, 1924-1949 and undated (Box 1)
    - Diary of trip, 1896
    - Funeral preparations for Eleanore Walton, 1957-1958
    - Hingham, Mass. and other family material, 1730-1828
    - Photographs, 1883-1919 and undated
    - General, 1865-1956 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Loring B. Walton Series
  Loring B. Walton, 1905-1975 and undated Diaries and journals, postcards, photographs and negatives, letters, writings, and clippings. This is the larger series of the two, consisting primarily of Walton's correspondence to and from his mother, Eleanore Walton. There are three folders for British Army officer A. Goderic A. Hodges. Categories are diaries, correspondence, miscellaneous, and pictures.
  - Diaries:
    - Diaries and journals, 1908-1919, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Journals, including postcards and some photographs, 1923, July
    - Journal, including postcards and photographs, 1923, July (Box 3)
    - Journal, including postcards, 1923 Aug., (2 folders)
  - Correspondence:
    - To mother, 1913-1919, July, (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - To mother, 1919-1923, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - From mother, 1911-1958, (2 folders)
    - Brewer, Wilmon, 1958-1972
    - France, Anatole, 1940
    - Hodges, A. Goderic A., 1930-1975, (3 folders)
    - Holleaux, Maurice, 1932 (Box 5)
    - Sforza, Count Carlo, 1933-1950
    - General, 1932-1975
  - Miscellaneous:
    - Duke University, 1950-1967 (Box 5)
    - Military service, 1918-1934
    - Wilson, Edmund, undated
    - Writings and speeches, 1905-1923 and undated
    - General, 1916-1929, 1963, and undated
  - Pictures:
    - Postcards and photograph of Wilson's inauguration, 1913 (Box 5)
    - Mounted photographs, 1919
    - Photographs:
      - General staff of Third Army, U.S.A., Coblenz on Rhine, 1919
      - Princeton, Harvard, Hingham, Mass., 1920
      - Postcards and photographs, 1921
      - Postcards and photographs, 1921 (Box 6)
      - Photograph of Romance Language Department, Duke University, 1947-1948
    - Photographic negatives:
      - Fort Douglas, Utah, 1920
      - Princeton, Harvard, 1920
      - Princeton, Harvard, Hingham, 1920
      - 1920, (2 folders)
- Oversize Materials
  - George and Eleanore Walton Series, 1868 and undated (Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 2)
- Addition (2003-0053) 1917-1968, (1 box)
  Addition (03-053)(175 items, .2 lin. ft.; dated 1917-1968) comprises materials of Loring Baker Walton, and consists primarily of scholarly correspondence and materials concerning his work on Anatole France and other projects (1932-1968). Also includes his class notes from Harvard (1917-1918), and from his training and service with the American Expeditionary Forces during World War I. This addition is unprocessed.
- Addition (2008-0184) 1891-1980 and undated, (1 box)
  Addition (08-184) (375 items, .4 lin. ft.; dated 1891-1980 and undated) contains primarily material related to Loring Baker Walton’s background and service with the AEF in WWI. Includes information regarding Walter family property settlements for land they owned in Germany that was damaged during WWII. There are also letters (1891-1951) for George E. and Eleanore C. Walter. This addition is unprocessed.